Congregational Club records, 1869-1961.
Congregational Library & Archives
Congregational Club records, 1869-1961.
RG1039
Congregational Library & Archives
1.79 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
This collection contains the records of the Congregational Club, fully established in April of 1869. This club served to create cameraderie between members of the Congregational community. This collection contains records through 1947, but the club continued to exist until it was disbanded at some point between 1978 and 1981. The collection contains event-related materials, administrative records, and necrologies.
Congregational Club (Boston, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Historical Note
On February 22, 1869 Rev. J. W. Wellman, D.D brought the idea of the Congregational Club to a Pastor's Meeting in Boston, Massachusetts. The club was fully established, with a constitution and officers, by April 20th of the same year. The goal of the club was to "energize Congregationalism" by encouraging cameraderie and cooperation among Congregationalists, particularly in the Boston area. The club fostered this community with monthly discussions, and formal social gatherings such as their Annual Festival and Forefathers' Day.
This collection contains records through 1947, but the club continued to exist until it was disbanded at some point between 1978 and 1981.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records documenting the activity of the Congregational Club from its inception in 1869 to 1961. It contains records relating to administration, events held by the club, and necrologies.
Arrangement
The Congregational Club records have been arranged into the three series listed below. Within each series materials have been primarily arranged in chronological order by start date. When appropriate, similar and continuous materials have been grouped together.
Series 1: Administration, 1869-1961
Series 2: Necrologies, 1870-1916
Series 3: Events, 1871-1944
Related Materials
Additional records related to the Congregational Club can be found in the Roslindale, Boston, Mass. Highland Congregational Church records, 1869-2006, RG4824.
Bibliography
"Rev. Rice, Congregational Club Boston 1972-1981 in the Roslindale, Boston, Mass. Highland Congregational Church records, 1869-2006, RG4824. The Congregational Library & Archives, Boston, MA."
Church societies.; Congregationalism--New England; Corporate minutes.; Necrologies.; Congregational Club (Boston, Mass.); Wellman, Joshua W. (Joshua Wyman) (1821-1915)
- Administration, 1869 1961; 1869-1961; 6 Folders; 34 Items; 5 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the Congregational Club's administrative records including meeting records, member lists, a constitution, bylaws, manuals, ballots, and reports.
  - Meeting Records, 1869 1877; 1869-1877 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Meeting Records, 1877 1890; 1877-1890 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Meeting Records, 1890 1904; 1890-1904 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Meeting Records, 1908 1923; 1908-1923 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Manuals, 1884 1927; 1884-1927 (Box 4)
  - Constitution & Bylaws, 1869 1877; 1869, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Announcements and Ballots, 1871 1947; 1871-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reports, 1872 1919; 1872-1919 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Member Lists, 1872 1945; 1872, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Christian Work, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Constitution, Bylaws, Member List, undated (Box 1, Volume 1)
- Necrologies, 1870 1916; 1870-1916; 7 Items
  This series contains obituaries, necrologies, and biographies of deceased members of the community.
  - Necrologies & Biographer Reports, 1872 1916; 1872-1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1870 1875; 1870-1875 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1879 1880; 1879-1880 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Notes for the Deceased, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Events, 1871 1944; 1871-1944; 1 Volume; 7 Folders
  This series includes records relating to various events held by the Congregational Club such as event announcements, tickets, programs, addresses, and a scrapbook.
  - Event Tickets, 1871 1944; 1871-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Forefathers' Night Programs & Announcements, 1873 1942; 1873-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellanies Scrapbook, 1882 1887; 1882-1887 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Our Present Movement in Theology, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ladies' Night & May Festival, 1880 1945; 1890-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Congregationalism in Boston - Its Present Condition, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Assorted Events, 1893 1944; 1893-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Annual Meetings, 1932 1940; 1932-1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)